<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A revindication of Psalme 105. 15. Touch not mine anointed, &amp;c. from some false glosses, now and heretofore obtruded upon it by Anabaptists: proving that this divine inhibition chiefly concerns subjects: who let them be never so Gods servants, yet are they not Gods anointed as well as kings. Being a reply to a late seditious pamphlet, called A vindication, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E245_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872498</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124936</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124936)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 42:E245[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A revindication of Psalme 105. 15. Touch not mine anointed, &amp;c. from some false glosses, now and heretofore obtruded upon it by Anabaptists: proving that this divine inhibition chiefly concerns subjects: who let them be never so Gods servants, yet are they not Gods anointed as well as kings. Being a reply to a late seditious pamphlet, called A vindication, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel, printer to the Universitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Prynne, William. A vindication of Psalm 105.15. (touch not mine anoynted, and doe my prophets no harme) from some false glosses lately obtruded on it by Royallists.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 31 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Vindication of Psalm 105.15. (touch not mine anoynted, and doe my prophets no harme) from some false glosses lately obtruded on it by Royallists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CV, 15 --  Comentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124936:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124936:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REVINDICATION <hi>OF</hi> PSALME 105.15. <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From ſome falſe gloſſes, now and hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obtruded upon it by Anabaptiſts:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proving</hi> That this Divine inhibition chiefly concerns Subjects: who let them be never ſo Gods ſervants, yet are they not Gods Anointed as well as Kings.</p>
            <p>Being a Reply to a late ſeditious Pamphlet, called A VINDICATION, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JUDE verſ. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Theſe be they who ſeparate themſelves, ſenſuall, having not the Spirit.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Theſe are murmurers, complainers, walking after their own luſts, and their mouth ſpeaketh great ſwelling words, having mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Likewiſe alſo theſe filthy dreamers defile the fleſh, deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by ROGER DANIEL, Printer to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> of <hi>Cambridge. Anno Dom.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:124936:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124936:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hy, <hi>A vindication of Pſalme</hi> 105.15? <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, &amp;c.</hi> As if the man would perverſely inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate to theſe miſunderſtanding times, that there were no other Text of Scripture to that ſelf-ſame ſenſe and ſcope; from which he would pretend to vindicate this. And ſo (this vindicated) the Truth it ſelf muſt quite fall to the ground. Elſe, wherefore keeps he ſuch a whittling about one ſlender ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row (as he takes it) when the quiver is full of ſtrong ſhafts, and ſuch as flie mainly at the mark? Thinks he the whole hedge muſt needs lie along, becauſe the thief tugs hard to ſteal one ſtake out of it? This houſe (like the houſe founded upon a rock) is built upon ſurer pillars, then to totter though one prop be wrencht away. No, no: I can aſſure him, the muſters are complete, and the cauſe will be ſtoutly maintained againſt him, though he would labour never ſo to invegle one ſingle man away from it.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, to deprave a Truth, which is factious hereſie: but there's as ill as that, to ſtrike at the perſon whom that truth concerns; which is villanous treachery. For why would he not have Kings here meant to be <hi>Gods anointed?</hi> becauſe ſuch are abſolutely inhibited here to be <hi>toucht.</hi> So then he would therefore invalide the truth of the thing, that ſo he might give licence to the injury of the fact. Princes (for him) might have been here alſo underſtood <hi>Gods Anointed,</hi> but that it is here ſo plainly inhibited to <hi>touch</hi> them. How to touch them? with a very malignant touch. For ſo the ancients in their tranſlation expound <hi>tangere,</hi> by <hi>malignari.</hi> We ſee then who are ſimply the Malignants; even thoſe that dare offer to <hi>touch the Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing he excepts againſt a ſingle man in this royall army, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will needs inſimulate him, to deny his colours; we will ſet him aſide a while, and have at him with double and trebble forces from another wing. At him? No. I hold it more honourable to retreat at firſt onſet, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then offer to skirmiſh with a ſeditious Pamphletter, againſt whom all victory is but loſſe and ſhame.</p>
            <p>Wherefore waving him (for he is prepoſſeſt) I earneſtly wiſh all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects (that are Chriſtian and godly) to be well inſtructed in thoſe words 1. Sam. 24.6, 10, 12. of their right meaning, of their true uſe. Which done throughly, then themſelves may be pleaſed to call in the man, and ask him. If here be not a conſcience fully convinced of a <hi>divine inhibition,</hi> when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124936:3"/>he ſaies, <hi>The Lord forbid.</hi> A phraſe (both here, and in many other places of Scripture) noting not onely an inhibition, but a conſcience convicted of that inhibition: and not onely a conviction, but a reſolution not to practiſe againſt it: and not onely not to practiſe againſt it himſelf; but not ſo much as yield or ſuffer others ſo to do. Ask him again, whether thoſe words (of <hi>ſtretching forth the hand against the Lords Anointed</hi>) be to be interpreted and applied <hi>not to Kings, but onely to ſubjects, and as ſubjects?</hi> ſurely the mans own ignorance is not ſo much, as that his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice dares now be peremptory: neither his malice ſo much, as to preſume he may here alſo obtrude upon others ignorance. If he have either know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or conſcience; he cannot but confeſſe, here's a Divine inhibition gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſubjects, not to Kings; who are (in a peculiar manner) <hi>the Lords Anointed,</hi> and not they.</p>
            <p>Let all true Subjects learn what <hi>David</hi> ſayes again, 1. Sam. 26.9, 10, 11. <hi>Who can stretch forth his hand againſt the Lords anointed?</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <hi>Who,</hi> in the univerſall and indefinite, to note, that no man ought to do ſuch an act, of what place or power, of what condition or concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſoever. He ſayes, <hi>and be guiltleſſe,</hi> to note, there's no humane cauſe or command can ſufficiently warrant hereunto: much leſſe can Jealouſies, ſuſpicions, ſuppoſalls, excuſes, pretenſes; which alſo have a guilt of their own, beſides that of the fact they would induce unto. In the 10. verſe, he leaves the <hi>Lords anointed</hi> in every thing, to the Judgement of the Lord himſelf; noting, that Kings are puniſhable for their offences, not to men, much leſſe their own Subjects, but are to be referred here in to God alone. Laſtly he ſayes. <hi>The Lord forbid,</hi> or <hi>the Lord keep me from:</hi> noting it to be a work of reſtraining grace, <hi>not to ſtretch forth the hand against the Lords anointed.</hi> The Fanatticks, out of their <hi>Enthuſiaſmes,</hi> do ill then to incite men hereunto, by making it a motion of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>But good Subjects, heed moreover the 2. Sam. 1, 14, 16. See here a juſt example of one, that did but pretend to practiſe contrarie to this awfull truth. The <hi>Amalekite</hi> had not once touched the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> to ſuch a fact. For ('tis evident in this Chapter, as alſo 1. Sam. 31. and 1. Chron. 10.) that King Saul dyed by his own act, yet certainly the vile wretch had a will to ſuch a deed; and that made him boaſt as if he had done it. Now to boaſt; and lie, and diſſemble, and pretend in buſineſſe of ſo high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and concerning ſo mighty a perſonage as that of a King; was of it ſelf worthy of ſevereſt puniſhment. And <hi>David</hi> by this example of Juſtice, lets us underſtand that it is Capitall but to intend or pretend violence to the Perſon of a Prince, the Lords Anointed. Yea, the villain, preſuming others conſcience to be as corrupt as his own, belyes himſelf in expectation of reward. (So there be many nowadayes that miſcheivouſly belie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have had hands in ſuch and ſuch perilous and unwarrantable facts, as indeed they durſt hardly approch; in preſumption to pleaſe men, and be applauded.) But this Caitiff was taken at his own word, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred for it: and ſo ought all ſuch to be ſerved, that dare but falſely boaſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124936:3"/>to have been actours in foul miſchief, amongſt men of honeſt conſcience. Yea, as this <hi>Amalekite</hi> did belie himſelf into a Treaſon, and worthily ſuffered for it: ſo has this Pamphleter (in this lie of his) little leſſe then treaſonably; and therefore ought to ſuffer in the cenſure of God, and good men. Beſides this <hi>Amalekite;</hi> why were Rechab and Baanah, 2. Sam. 4.10, 11, 12. Shimei, 2. Sam. 16.5. 1. King. 2.46. Zimri, 1. King. 16.9, 10, 18, 20. Bigthan and Tereſh, Eſther 2.21, 22, 23. Zabad and Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabad, 2. King. 12.20, 21. and, 2. Chron. 24.26. and Chap. 25. verſe 3. The ſervants of Amon, 2. King. 21.23, 24. Why (I ſay) were all theſe arraigned, condemned, executed (ſome according to the Laws of God, ſome of men, ſome of Nature, as we reade) and that for <hi>touching the Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed,</hi> with a traiterous touch (whether of hand, mouth, mind or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) if there was no Law or inhibition concerning Kings properly to forbid them ſo to do. Doubtleſſe the Penalty (ſo ſeverely executed upon them) evicts that there was (even to this purpoſe) an inhibiting Law, both of God, of Nature, of Nations, and of State.</p>
            <p>Further, Let Chriſtian Subjects and conſcientious lay adviſedly to heart thoſe words of the Apoſtle, Romans 13.1, 2, 5. And if the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> be properly Kings, then whom there is not an higher here on earth, and are onely and immediately under him, that is the <hi>Higheſt</hi> of all (which of neceſſity muſt be conceded, if theſe words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> be compared with theſe of S. <hi>Peter</hi> 1. Pet. 2.13, 14. For what S. <hi>Paul</hi> here requires <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> S. <hi>Peter</hi> there appropriates it to the King, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: nay, and makes him to be the <hi>Higher</hi> or <hi>Supreme,</hi> in a diſtinction to the inferiour Governour or Magiſtrate.) And if to <hi>reſist</hi> (take it as the letter ſounds) be an act of farre more daring inſolence, then to <hi>touch;</hi> then ask this Man once more (and you ſhall eaſily have his heart and intent) why this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inhibition (<hi>of reſiſting Higher Powers</hi>) muſt needs be peculiarly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Kings: and that divine inhibition (<hi>of touching the Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed</hi>) muſt by no means be properly ſo meant? Tell him, he is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo tender of the <hi>Sacred Perſon,</hi> as he pretends: that ſeeing he can ſay nothing againſt that Place, where the <hi>Ordinance is not to be reſiſted;</hi> he onely ſeeks to cavill at that Place, where the <hi>Perſon is not to be touched.</hi> And if (to excuſe himſelf) he anſwer that he meant not to deny the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Truth (for he ha's confeſt it) nor yet to invalide the true intent of other Texts, that might well be produc'd to ſuch a purpoſe; but onely to vindicate this of the Pſalmiſt in particular from the larger application (as he yields) to the ſtricter letter: To him I now reply; that I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this his ſpecious precept, when I have ſuch evident reaſons for his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious intent: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If he were ſatisfied with this Truth (that <hi>the Lords Anointed is not to be touched, nor the Higher Power reſiſted</hi>) why then labours he to vindicate one text from it, when he knows, there are beſides ſo many to be produced for it? So that it is more then manifeſt, it is not a miſapplyed proof (as he pretends) but the main Truth of all, that he ſtrikes at, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124936:4"/>that the ill affected and eaſily blinded through a conceived vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of one Place will think but ſlightly of all other Places to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If he did onely intend ingenuouſly to vindicate this place of the Pſalme; then what do thoſe other places of Scripture crouded in the Title Page; not onely ſo impertinent to the pretended vindication; but ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious, ſo ſcandalous; and (that I may not ſay treaſonable) merely tending to faction, to ſedition! Even that very thing argues evidently, he never ment to vindicate the ſingle place of Scripture at the top: but onely to calumniate and inſtigate, by thoſe many impertinences of abuſed Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture at the bottom of his Title Page. As indeed he doth by all thoſe miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued and miſapplied Scriptures, this ſeditious Libill quite throughout. Thus, without doubt, you have his whole intent.</p>
            <p>But now let us examine him according to his pretenſes. He would vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that verſe of the Pſalme <hi>from ſome falſe gloſſes lately obtruded on it by Royalliſts.</hi> Spoken as like a <hi>vulgariſt</hi> as may be. Whoſe common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture is of more errour then the <hi>Vulgar Tranſlation</hi> it ſelf. Since he is ſuch a zealous vindicator of texts from falſe gloſſes; why undertakes he none of thoſe many hundreds of places, corrupted and wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Papists,</hi> and by the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> both Authours and Fautours of the greateſt hereſies and ſchiſmes? Nay why vindicates he not this very <hi>Pſalme and verſe,</hi> from the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> that have taken it from Kings, and given it to Popes? As for the Papiſts, he nibbles indeed a little at them, and letteth you underſtand, their falſe gloſſe upon the place hath been long ſince exploded: But yet he is envious and tells you not by whom. To ſay truth, it was done, not by any <hi>vulgariſt,</hi> or <hi>Separatiſt;</hi> but by ſuch as he calls <hi>Rovalliſts, and Court-Divines;</hi> Men of learning, piety, loyalty, order, diſcretion. Nay, and why vindicates he not this very <hi>Pſalme and verſe,</hi> from the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> that have taken it from both Kings and Prieſts, and given it to the Common people? Hah! the <hi>Anabaptiſts?</hi> why it is onely in their juſtification and behalf, that he is ſo eager in the vindication, who have much abuſed the place, to extirpate prelacy, confound Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, and induce Anarchie, by planting here (their own Idole of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) Parity. Hence ſeeking to heighten the vulgar, firſt to a ſpirituall pride, and ſo to a civil rebellion. As well witneſſes, that his main Collection hereupon, with all the dependances; <hi>That ſubjects are Gods anoynted, as well as Kings.</hi> &amp;c. which ſounds paradoxall to any ſenſible eare. And mark me well; if (together with that) all other the <hi>Proofs</hi> in this <hi>vindication</hi> prove not ſuch.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Paradox. <hi>That this divine inhibition, was given to Kings, not to ſubjects. Given</hi> has a fallacy in it. Means he by way of direction, or by way of obligation? If by way of obligation; then this muſt follow, That Kings are here inhibited to <hi>touch</hi> or harm ſubjects: but ſubjects not inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited here, but rather left at liberty to touch and harm Kings. But as for the mere direction. 1. It is not ſo palpable, that theſe words were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124936:4"/>to Kings. And therefore the ancient Fathers (whom this man will have conclude after his expoſition) ſay plainly that theſe words are not to be found in the hiſtory: but if God uttered them, it was by an Angel or ſome ſecret inſtinct. And although it be ſaid in the preceding verſe of the Pſalme, <hi>he reproved Kings for their ſakes:</hi> yet 'tis not ſo evident and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that he reproved there by this ſaying. For as much as <hi>Saying</hi> is not in the Hebrue. And therefore this man is ſomewhat too confident; when <hi>(ſaying even to Kings themſelves)</hi> he peremptorily gloſſes upon a word not found in the text. 2. If we look to the parties literally and hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically here concerned <hi>(Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob)</hi> their ſtory plainly tells, that the inhibition <hi>(touch not)</hi> is not ſo much directed from God to the Kings: as from the Kings to their ſubjects concerning them. Gen. 12.20. Gen. 26.11. 3. Say this were directed to Kings; yet was it not to Kings in regard of their own ſubjects. For <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> &amp;c. may not be ſaid to be ſubject unto thoſe Heathen Kings. 4. It does not alwayes imply, to whom is the direction, theirs is alſo the Obligation. For we find ſundry both precepts and promiſes in the Scripture, that are ſpoken to one, and yet concerning another. 5. Theſe words ſimply conſidered as concerning the <hi>Lords Anoynted</hi> may have in them the force of a promiſe, as well as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition; and be directed to Princes generally for their faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, rather then their charge and obligation. 6. David is inſpired to call the patriarchs <hi>Gods Anoynted</hi> knowing them to be the ſame duputies, images, and vicegerents of God (as the times were) as he himſelf was. 7. 'Tis abſurd and ſeditious to ſay, that theſe words were ſpoken onely to Kings, and not to ſubjects; as if the one were ſolely included, and the other here excluded from their duty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Paradoxe, <hi>That theſe words were originally ſpoken and intended onely of Abraham, Iſaac</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Who were neither actuall Kings,</hi>—<hi>nor Kings and Prieſts by office</hi>—<hi>and they were meant of them, not as they were Kings and Priests.</hi>—<hi>but as forainers and ſubjects</hi>—<hi>and are to be interpreted and applied, not to Kings and Prieſts, as they are ſuch</hi> — <hi>but to the faithfull,</hi> though, and as ſubjects. In ſuch a throng of Paradoxes, the man is ſo overſeen, that he is forſt in ſome things to thwart and contradict himſelf. As that Abraham, Iſaac &amp;c. were neither Kings nor Prieſts; and again, that theſe words were not meant of them, as they were Kings and Prieſts. Where he grants the ration; onely denyes the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Item, that theſe words are to be applied not to Kings; and yet he willingly and cordially profeſſes the place may be <hi>aptly applyed</hi> to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſafety. But where he happens to favour himſelf, let us now ſee the truth and the Scriptures contradicting him. 1. When he faith, <hi>That theſe words were originally ſpoken and intended of Abraham</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Originally,</hi> it may be; if he mean hiſtorically; but not <hi>Onely.</hi> For thus he barres him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his own ſenſe in the generall; while he ſolely tyes it up to this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. <hi>Spoken</hi> it may be too; but not <hi>intended.</hi> For there's no queſtion but <hi>David</hi> intended here to include himſelf and his Poſterity, as <hi>The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124936:5"/>Lords Anointed:</hi> as appears in that he made it for a conſtant and publick Pſalme of Thankſgiving, 1. Chron. 16.7. Now acts and inſtances of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and ſolemne Services ought not to be reſtrained to temporary or private concernments. 2. <hi>That Abraham, Iſaac, &amp;c. were neither actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Kings and Prieſts, neither Kings and Prieſts by office.</hi> The Man is mightily deceived: They were Kings and Prieſts (though not ſo rituall and ceremoniall as afterwards) yet actuall and by office. It is too too plain againſt him; the Patriarchs governed not onely in Oeconomie, but in Politie, even ſo farre as in higheſt affairs, <hi>viz.</hi> of life and death, in peace and warre. They likewiſe built altars, and offered ſacrifice. God calls <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham a Prophet,</hi> Gen. 20.7. and the children of <hi>Heth</hi> call him <hi>a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince</hi> or King, Gen. 23.6. And as they called the Patriarch a King; ſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> calls a King a Patriarch, Acts 2.29. ſo little difference he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood between them. Neither was it other for ſubſtance then one govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, that began in the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> went through the <hi>Judges,</hi> and ended or reſted in <hi>Kings.</hi> They being all equally of one type, deputation, preſentation, vicegerencie. 3. <hi>That the Patriarchs were ſubjects.</hi> That's a kind of Bull or contradiction, to ſay, Patriarchs and Subjects: for the word Patriarch ſounds ſuch a thing as King. And they were ſuch, as is proved above. And Kings are but Patriarchs or chief governing Fathers of their Countreys. How were the Patriarchs Subjects to thoſe amongſt whom they ſojourned? When as <hi>Abraham</hi> acknowledging himſelf a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journer,</hi> they accounted him nevertheleſſe <hi>a mighty Prince amongſt them,</hi> Gen. 23.4, 6. when themſelves acknowledged that <hi>they were mightier then they,</hi> Gen. 26.16. when battell was given by one of theſe, to foure of thoſe at once with victory thereupon, Gen. 14.14. when they were glad to treat with them as free Princes, to article and covenant with them for mutuall priviledges and indemnitie, Gen. 21.21, 22, 23. Gen. 26.28, 29, In one word, If the Patriarchs were ſubjects to thoſe amongſt whom they ſojourned (as this man falſely impoſes upon all Expoſitours) then let him ſhew us from them, where the Patriarchs did appeal to their Laws; (either for matter of Policie or Religion) and whether it was lawfull for them ſo to do? or if they were at any time ſubdued to that ſubjection? But ſince it is ſo clear, that the Patriarchs were not Subjects but Princes; now then it follows neceſſarily, that theſe words of the Pſalme are to be underſtood of them, not as Subjects, but as Princes; and in that reſpect chiefly they are here called <hi>Gods Anointed.</hi> So that now the ſenſe and ſumme of theſe words are literally and genuinely thus to be collected and apprehended; as God ſhould ſay, O ye Kings and Princes of the Nations, <hi>Touch not,</hi> with any offer or violence, <hi>Mine,</hi> whom I have choſen to my ſelf before all the nations of the earth: <hi>Mine Anointed,</hi> ſuch as are conſecrated to be Kings and Princes in a more ſpeciall manner then your ſelves: and have more right (by my promiſe) to dwell and rule in this land, then you: Nay, to whom I (whoſe the earth is and all that dwell therein) have given and ſubjected you. So that it is thus more then manifeſt that God ſpeaks theſe words of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124936:5"/>the Pſalme to the nations, even the greateſt and proudeſt of them, whom he had execrated already and devoted into ſubjection to the Patriarchs and Princes whom he had voted and conſecrated either to ſubdue or extirpate them as enemies; or elſe (as ſervants and ſubjects) to reigne and rule over them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Paradox, <hi>That the People and Subjects are Gods Anointed, as well as Kings.</hi> The man does ſeem cordially to profeſſe, <hi>that Kings (in ſacred writ) are commonly called Gods anointed, &amp;c.</hi> And to this purpoſe he heaps his proofs in figures and not in words at length. And that's not ſo cordially, as cunningly done. For the many proofs that are againſt him them he gives you but groſſely, and in a clutter; as if it did even irk him to recite them. But the few proofs that he would have make for him, them he drawls out at length. And why ſo? Becauſe did he not curtall thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer texts, the very recitall would ſufficiently confute him. And all ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men might reade at once, and perceive, That Kings are not onely <hi>Gods Anointed</hi> in the generall; but by a ſpeciall Emphaſis called the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi> Nor yet <hi>commonly ſo called;</hi> but really ſo conſecrated. And not onely is it with an oyl of outward rite and Ceremony: but according to an Ordinance of perpetuall truth and myſtery. As ſhall further appear in examination of the ſo vehemently urged proofs for his opinion. <hi>viz.</hi> Pſal. 28.8. where the <hi>Anointed</hi> in the 8. verſe, he will have to bee the <hi>People</hi> mentioned in the 9, verſe. When as the 8. verſe ha's the full ſenſe in it ſelf. And not onely ſo, but <hi>David</hi> there diſtinguiſhes betwixt the <hi>Plebs</hi> (as they tranſlate it) and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctus.</hi> And ſpeaks of them in the Plurall; of himſelf (for Gods annointed) in the ſingular number. Neither is it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for <hi>David</hi> in the Pſalmes, to ſpeak of himſelf in the third Perſon; as appears Pſal. 18.50. which is the next place, he ſeeks to wreſt to his purpoſe. Where ſince he cannot deny <hi>(his Anointed)</hi> to be <hi>David and his ſeed:</hi> he therefore will have David and his ſeed there, to be <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Elect.</hi> Which ſenſe (we deny not) may be orthodoxally admitted in the allegorie: but by his leave, we may not ſuffer the genuine ſenſe of the letter to be rejected; unleſſe he can make it plain, there is ſuch an abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the literall that it cannot ſtand with reaſon, but muſt neceſſarily therefore be tranſferred to another ſenſe. Now theſe words in the bare and expreſſe letter are fair and full ſenſe, either backwards or forwards; <hi>His King, his anointed, David: David, his anointed, his King.</hi> Which words (either way) will primarily bear no other ſenſe then this, that <hi>David</hi> propoſes himſelf to be Gods <hi>Anointed,</hi> as he was a <hi>King.</hi> And is not this a moſt excellent <hi>Vindicatour</hi> now, and ſincere? that pretending (as his main work) to reſcue and rectifie one verſe of a <hi>Pſalme,</hi> according to the originall ſenſe and meaning; and yet to that purpoſe, ſticks not to falſifie and diſtort too? His next Place is Hab. 3.13. Is It poſſible that the man ſhould be ſo blinded, as not to diſtinguiſh there, betwixt, <hi>for thy People and with thine anointed?</hi> The words expreſſely teach, that the <hi>Prophet</hi> there ſpeaks of them as two. As namely, <hi>for them,</hi> whoſe benefit was the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124936:6"/>end; <hi>with him,</hi> whoſe authority was the means. It is very plain from the two preceding verſes, that by the <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> intends the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and by the <hi>anointed, Joſhua,</hi> their Captain. And I pray now, whether was <hi>Joſhua</hi> a Subject, or a ſupreme Magiſtrate? Thus he is quite out of the old Teſtament; where Kings and Princes (in a peculiar manner) are above 30 times called <hi>Gods anointed.</hi> Now let us ſee how he would fain help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the New, <hi>viz.</hi> 2. Cor. 1.21. Now, though I might here diſtinguiſh of anointing; yet the exactneſſe of the <hi>Apostles</hi> own expreſſion bids me here ſave the labour. <hi>Hath anointed</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the People of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi>) not you, but <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>hath establiſhed us with you;</hi> it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely interpreted of his Officiall rather then Perſonall unction; as of his Apoſtleſhip, preiſthood, miniſtry; to which God had anointed or ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and had eſtabliſht or confirmed him with, or amongſt them. But what ſay we to that Place he cites, 1. Joh. 2.27. Here I yield, that Gods faithfull People, though Subjects, have an <hi>anointing:</hi> but I dare not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inferre hence, that they are (in all points) Gods anointed, much leſſe, as well as Kings. For the <hi>Anointing</hi> here, is the holy Ghoſt, and his gifts; who though he anoint all the Elect to the generall calling of Chriſtians; yet not to the ſpeciall callings of Kings, and Prieſts. All true Chriſtians are anointed with the ſpirituall unction, that of regeneration: but not with the regall unction, that of inauguration; nor with the ſacerdotall unction, that of miniſtration. Laſtly to thoſe Places, 1. Pet. 2.5, 9. Rev. 1.6. and 5.10. Thoſe Places are ſufficiently cleared by all orthodox Divines (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you call them <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts</hi>) againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> who blindly preſuming hence, of an equall account with God; would hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on proudly account themſelves equall with all men. And thus abuſe thoſe places, as arguments for their fanatick Parity, both in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. But the learned and orthodox (as I ſay) diſſolve thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (and in that reſolve all good Chriſtians) by diſtinguiſhing: As namely, that all true Chriſtians are Kings and Prieſts. 1. Comparatively, in reference to the heathen and uncalled: as may well be gathered from thoſe words in the old Teſtament, Exod. 19.6. from which theſe in the New, are taken, and applied. Yea and <hi>S. Peter</hi> expreſſes ſo much, a <hi>royall Prieſthood,</hi> that is, <hi>a choſen generation, a peculiar people, which in times past were not a People.</hi> 2. Spiritually, and in a large ſenſe, As S. Peter alſo expounds himſelf in the one place, <hi>a royall Prieſthood, that is an holy nation, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifices.</hi> And ſo doth S. John in the other <hi>Kings and Priests,</hi> not to men, but <hi>to God.</hi> Offering up ſacrifices of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and praiſes; reigning and ruling over their own carnall luſts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences. And thus much the man himſelf cannot but confeſſe, <hi>That all true Chriſtians are Kings and Prieſts in a ſpirituall ſenſe, though they be but Subjects its a Politick ſenſe.</hi> Having ſaid thus much himſelf, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what it is the Man would now contend for. Let Chriſtians be ſubject in a politick ſenſe (yet not merely politick neither but out of Conſcience, and with reſpect to the divine ordinance) and who will deny them to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124936:6"/>Kings and Prieſts in a ſpirituall ſenſe? Will any Chriſtian King envy his Subjects the eternall crown of glory (as he ſpeaks) and their reigning with <hi>Chriſt</hi> for ever, ſo they intrench not upon his temporall Crown; nor uſurp to reigne with him here on Earth? After this his own diſtinction, mark now what is become of his Propoſition, <hi>That all the faithfull are Gods anointed, as well as Kings.</hi> Belike he means it onely in a ſpirituall ſenſe: and then it is no more, then if he had ſaid thus, That all good Chriſtians are Chriſtians as well as Kings; becauſe Chriſtian ſignifies An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed.</p>
            <p n="4">Paradox, <hi>That it is more unlawfull for Kings to make warre upon their ſubjects, by way of offence, then for ſubjects to take up armes againſt Kings, by way of defence.</hi> All this is beſides the vindication of the Pſalme; I ſhall therefore be the leſſe upon it. Otherwiſe this very point were worth a treatiſe: which is not to be lookt for in a pamphlets refutation. That poore piece of the <hi>Pſalme</hi> is but the pretenſe, here is the matter intended. While he ſtumbles about that, he hopes the ignorant and ill-affected will ſwallow down this. But he ſhall never reſolve nor perſwade wiſe men and conſciencious; unleſſe he will take pains not to determine raſhly, but to diſcuſſe orderly, and inſtruct ſoundly, in theſe 3. points at leaſt, 1. What warre offenſive, and defenſive is. 2. How farre forth a man may be defenſive onely and yet not offenſive. 3. Whether the defenſive, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, be on this ſide, or that. To determine all theſe aright, were to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie conſciences: but to urge and inveigh upon ſuppoſalls, is to intangle them ſo much the more. Yet conſider a little what he ſaies upon ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>It is more unlawfull;</hi> that argues ſome unlawfulneſſe, as well on one ſide, as another. <hi>Subjects may take up armes merely defenſive;</hi> Not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive then in any caſe; much leſſe merely offenſive. Why may they do ſo, as he ſaies? becauſe they are <hi>Gods anoynted too.</hi> Is that his main reaſon for their taking up armes? well. And how are they <hi>Gods anoynted?</hi> He ſaies himſelf, in a <hi>Spirituall ſenſe.</hi> Why then, by the forte of his own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their armes ought onely to be ſpirituall. For they are not (as he grants) Gods anoynted in a <hi>Politick ſenſe;</hi> and therefore politick their armes muſt not be. But he ha's other under-reaſons. Becauſe <hi>God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Kings to injure or oppreſſe their ſubjects, being his anoynted faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians.</hi> So are they inhibited though their ſubjects were Pagans. And God hath likewiſe inhibited ſubjects to reſiſt and injure Kings. Item, <hi>God hath puniſhed and plagued Kings for ſo doing.</hi> Note then, that it is in God to puniſh them. And, beſides that he delivers them to Kings to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them; God will likewiſe plague ſubjects if they offend their Kings. Item, <hi>that there is no law of God or man, that hath given Authority to Kings, to injure or oppreſſe their ſubjects</hi>—<hi>wage warre againſt them.</hi> &amp;c. How much leſſe is there for ſubjects then? Item, <hi>that there is an Oath at the Coronation for Kings to obſerve:</hi> So is there for ſubjects likewiſe, <hi>an Oath of Allegiance.</hi> But why perſiſt I in replying to theſe? Himſelf ſaies, he ranks his reaſons to clear this point, <hi>That Kings muſt no more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124936:7"/>offer violence to their ſubjects perſons or eſtates (without legall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and juſt cauſe) then they offer violence to their Kings.</hi> A point as clear as the noon day though he had produced never a reaſon for it. Beſide theſe, and many his other inſtances of Scripture, although true in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to be regarded with tremblings: yet thus abuſed by this vile man, they are onely to be anſwered with indignation and abhorring: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are urged upon falſe grounds and ſuppoſitions, and with a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious and ſeditious intent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Paradox, <hi>That Kings were created by; and for their ſubjects,</hi> &amp;c. The reſt of it is ſo ſawey, that it is not for a modeſt man to repeat. And this alſo is quite beſides the propoſed vindication: and ſerves onely to ſpeak the intention of the Authour, Sedition. Yet is this he ſaies, as falſe, as ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, quite contrary to Scriptures. As. Prov. 8.15, 16. <hi>By me Kings reigne</hi> (ſaies God) and therefore not by men. Dan. 4.2. <hi>The moſt High giveth the Kingdome to whomſoever he will;</hi> and not they. Rom. 13.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>The higher Powers are Gods ordinance,</hi> and not mans. <hi>Gods Miniſters</hi> they are, and therefore not the <hi>Peoples Servants.</hi> Why are they called <hi>Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82.6. John 10.34, 35. but becauſe they are immediately from God, and repreſent God here on earth, as types and images of Gods divine providence, Chriſts Kingly office, and the Angelicall order: yea and as the perfection of humane ſociety and of the Communion of Saints? What ſay they; when even wicked Kings are Gods ordinance. 1. Sam. 12.13. and ſent of God, not for their own ſo much, as for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſinne, Prov. 28.2. We ſay, there are foure ends of a Kings being: the firſt is Gods glory; the ſecond is his own Salvation; the third is the good of the Church; the fourth is the welfare of the State, (which conſiſts as well in puniſhing, as rewarding, Rom. 13.3, 4.) Now becauſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are one end; will they therefore claim to be the whole efficient? though the people may ſecondarily, and in ſome circumſtances, be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſed; as in election (where any ſuch cuſtome is) in the inauguration, the Counſell, the aſſiſtance,  yet can they have no right of challenge to the ſubſtance, or primary fundamentall, the Ordinance, the Power, which is of God.</p>
            <p>Yet let us take the beſt of this man as well as the worſt. His intent (he ſaies) <hi>is not to foment this unnaturall deſtructive warre,</hi> &amp;c. It was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable for any man to ſay otherwiſe. And therefore even thoſe that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it are notwithſtanding aſhamed to proclaim it. But he profeſſes further; <hi>that Kings are Gods Anoynted, and in that reſpect, their Perſons are ſacred; and no violence ought to be exerciſed upon their perſons, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by their ſubjects.</hi> As he confeſſes, is clear, 1. Sam. 24.3. to 12, 17, 18, 19. and chap. 26.7. to 25.2. Sam. 1.2. to 7. Nevertheleſſe, this is not ſo cordially ſpoken as he pretends. Becauſe he conceals a great part of the truth. For Kings are to be preſerved inviolable, not onely in their perſons; but likewiſe in their Name and Honour, as is alſo clear, Exod. 22.28. Eccles. 10.20. Alſo in their Government and Authority; Rom. 13.1, 2.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124936:7"/>Jude 8. As alſo in their rights and revenews, Matth. 22.21. Rom. 13.7. Theſe be matters worthy of a ſerious treatiſe by it ſelf (ſcarce to be meddled with in a by-confutation) to the intent people may know, that all Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and obedience of ſubjects, is not merely tyed to the perſon of a Prince. And therefore that a care or zeal to the perſon, is not to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in an injury or neglect to all the reſt.</p>
            <p>But I hold my duty here done to revindicate Pſalme 105.15. from ſuch falſe gloſſes as are notoriouſly obtruded on it by him here: and have been heretofore by (his like) the Anabaptiſts. Now therefore his proofs all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Paradoxall; let us (ere we end) look a little into his Authorities. His Authorities? where are they? why he ſayes, S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> with ſundry other Expoſitours, conclude of the ſenſe of this place according to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He but ſayes ſo: but let us heare and ſee what S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf, and others ſay indeed upon the place.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moves this queſtion, How the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> could be called <hi>anointed, antequam eſſet unctio,</hi> before the regall anointing as yet was. It is very plain he ſpeaks of the regall anointing; for he addes immediately, <hi>Ex qua hoc nomen impoſitum eſt Regibus:</hi> by which anointing the name <hi>Anointed</hi> is attributed to Kings. So that the ſumme of the Fathers <hi>quare</hi> is onely this, Why this name <hi>anointed</hi> (uſuall and proper to Kings) ſhould be ſpoken of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> while as yet no ſuch unction was in uſe? And it is to be ſupplyed in anſwer, That the regall unction as yet was not in the rituall way of it; but in the virtuall way it was. And if the Man think to ſnatch advantage, becauſe the Father ſpeaks at large, <hi>ideo Chriſti, quia etiamſi latenter, jam tamen Chriſtiani.</hi> That the Patriarchs might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not amiſſe be called <hi>anointed,</hi> becauſe they were even then Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, though veiled. Let him look before that, and he ſhall find him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding it in a ſtraiter ſenſe: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ergò illi jam tunc Chriſti appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur? nam Prophet as illos fuiſſe legimus.</hi> Why were the Patriarch; then called <hi>anointed?</hi> becauſe (as we reade) they were Prophets. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that (as the firſt ſenſe) ſpeaking of the ſpeciall anointing; he males the ſame to begin and reſt onely in Kings. <hi>Quod à Saule coepit, cui Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid ſucceſs it in regno, at que indè caeteri &amp; reges Judae, &amp; reges Iſrael, contimtatione ſacratae conſuetudinis ungebantur.</hi> Which name <hi>anointed</hi> began in Saul, whom David ſucceeded in the kingdome, and thence was the ſacred rite continued to the ſeverall kings of Iſrael and Judah. Now let the Man ſhew us how S. Auguſtine excludes kings here from being Gods <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed,</hi> or (reſpectively) expounds it of Subjects, or once intimates here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon that ſubjects are Gods Anointed as well as Kings.</p>
            <p>S. Hierome vindicates this place of the Pſalme juſtly againſt certain Jewiſh Doctours, who in hatred to <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, the true Meſſiah, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly ſeemed to argue hence, That none were to be called <hi>Chriſti, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed,</hi> that were not anointed with the Regall unguent. Whereupon he inſerres, <hi>Ecce, ante Legem, Patriarchae, non uncti regali unguento Chriſti dicuntur.</hi> Behold, before the Law, the Patriarchs are called Anointed;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124936:8"/>which were not anointed with the regall unction. And that he means ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially. And even that intimates that Kings, which (ſince the Law) are not anointed ſo materially and ſo ritually, are nevertheleſſe virtually and divinely, Gods anointed. Further, leſt any ſhould imagine, that he ſhould exempt Kings from being ſpecially underſtood in this place; he elſewhere applies it to them alone. As commenting upon Iſai. 45.1. Where God calls King <hi>Cyrus</hi> his anointed, and that according to the manner of the Hebrews, whoſe regall enſigne was anointing; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde &amp; Saul Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Domini dicitur, &amp; in Pſalmis legimus, Nolite tangere Chriſtos me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os.</hi> Whereupon (ſayes the Father) Saul is called the Lords anointed; and likewiſe we reade in the Pſalme, <hi>Touch not mineanointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two be the chief of the ancient Expoſitours whom <hi>Proſper, Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, Caſſiodore,</hi> venerable <hi>Bede, Bruno,</hi> and others do follow, diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed moſtly betwixt the materiall, and the ſpirituall Chryſme or unction. But it behoves to underſtand the reaſon of this warineſſe in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning. It was principally becauſe the hereticall <hi>Rabbines</hi> ſtrove here to exclude <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the ſchiſmaticall <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſtrive here to exclude Kings. We conclude therefore againſt them both, making up the true and full ſenſe of the verſe of this Pſalme, with that of another, <hi>viz.</hi> Pſal. 45. Though all Chriſtians be Gods anointed in a ſpirituall ſenſe; yet as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Kings; (one in the myſticall, the other in the litetall ſenſe) <hi>God, even their God, hath anointed them above their fellows.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be it properly and ſpecially, not onely ſaid, but laid to the Conſciences of all men, young and old, rich and poore, high and low, many or few,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:124936:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
